Okay, in this video then,
we are going to cover a very
important tool called
Funding Limit Reconciliation.
Now we already covered a couple of
important tools for cost management,
and those were the estimating methods,
they're analogous estimating, parametric
and so and so forth, that was on a
separate video.
Those were tools and techniques of cost
management.
This is another very important tool and
technique.
It's called Funding Limit Reconciliation.
Eventually what funding limit
reconciliation is, it is reconciling the
amount of work that needs to be done with
funding limits imposed or the actual
funding received by senior management or
by your customer.
So senior management a
lot of times, they will limit
the amount of money that
can be received on a project.
At the beginning of a project,
you don't necessarily get your entire
funding at the beginning of the project.
No, you're going to get your funding at
various points along the project.
Usually tied to some type of milestone.
Once we've completed this work,
we're going to get this much funding.
Once we've reached this milestone,
Why do you not always get your funding
right at the beginning?
Well, first of all, because you want to
control the expenses
throughout the project.
And then secondly, we don't want to have
these peaks and valleys, right,
throughout the organization.
The organization themselves, they only
have a certain amount of funding that they
can actually release at various points
along the project.
We don't suddenly want to start,
you know, spending too much money and then
having too little money and so and so
forth.
The organization themselves want to
control the cash flow for the organization.
So they're going to have a certain amount
of, you know, cash that they will release
at various points throughout the year and
so you are going to be reconciling the
work that needs to be done you know with
this cash flow now with the amount of
funding that is actually being received
right so funding limit reconciliation then
is reconciling the amount of work that
needs to be done with funding limits
imposed right so these are then funding
limits throughout the year or the actual
you know the customer's ability to
actually pay for the work right management
themselves have a fixed budget,
right, that they can own a release during
a particular time of the year, right,
or a particular time period, right?
So again, so that they can regulate the
cash flow of the organization.
So let me just give you a couple of very
simple examples on this.
So first example here.
So let's say our project,
right, we've estimated
it's going to cost a
million dollars, right?
It's a million dollar project,
right?
Just to use some nice, easy numbers here.
Now, senior management
right at the beginning, they
tell us they can only
release $250,000 per quarter.
On this project, it's a
million dollar project, right,
but they cannot release more
than $250,000 per quarter.
So a very minimum, then we know that this
project is going to take four quarters,
it's going to be a one-year project at a
very minimum.
We can't suddenly
decide, all right, it's a million
dollar project, let's try
and do this in six months.
Well, no, we won't be able to get the
funding for that, right?
In order to get the funding,
a senior management
can only release
$250,000 per quarter, right?
They want to regulate the cash flow for
the organisation.
And so we then, we are going to plan our
work and develop our schedule based on
this funding, based on this funding limit,
$250,000 per quarter.
So that is an example of funding limit
reconciliation.
Another example, again, this project,
is going to cost a million dollars.
Let's say we've already planned our work.
We've planned all of the work for this
project.
We've planned our milestone, all of our
milestones.
We've planned our schedule.
We planned who's going to be working on
each deliverable and so on and so forth.
They've planned all the work.
And this is how much is going to cost.
Now, that needs to be baseline.
We need to send it to
our senior management,
or our key stakeholders
for their approval.
for their sign-off.
Now, at that point, senior
management might turn round
and say, all right, well, we
have some funding limits now.
And so for year one, we can only release
these funds, right?
So in quarter one, we can only release
$150,000.
In quarter two, we can only release
$200,000.
In quarter three, we can go up to
$250,000, but then in quarter four,
we're back to $200,000.
This is all the funds that we can release,
right?
This is just for year one.
Then, you know, year two, right?
Then they'll have a separate, right?
We're just looking at year one here.
So now that they've given
you this, these funding limits,
now we need to go back and
we need to readjust our plan.
We need to readjust our schedule based on
these funding limits.
Right, now we need to go back.
And, you know, if our quarter one
expenses, if initially it was,
something like 250,000, right, then now
senior management can only release 150.
Well, we need to do something about that,
right?
So we're going to reschedule our work.
We might use some alternate resources,
right, move activities around from one
deliverable to another deliverable,
completely reschedule the whole work.
That is known as funding limit
reconciliation.
There's a couple of examples then of
funding limit reconciliation.
Another example of funding limit
reconciliation can also be, say,
the customer's ability to actually pay for
the work.
They have given you the scope of the
project.
They've given you the requirements.
You've come up with the scope.
You've come up with the cost.
And this cost is more than what the
customer was expecting.
Whether it's an internal project or an
external project, whether it's an internal
customer or an external customer, it's
costing more than what they were expecting.
So now they tell you, well, you need to
reduce your cost by, say, 10%.
Right.
So now you need to go back.
Again, you need to re-look
at your work, reschedule your
work, use alternate resources
to try and get your costs down.
So that is what funding limit
reconciliation is.
Reconciling the amount of work that needs
to be done with funding limits imposed,
right, or the actual funding received as
well.
Right.
So as you're executing, right,
you might have been expecting say $100,000
for this particular deliverable senior
management might turn round and say,
you know, we can't release that much now,
I need to various reasons.
And so now we need to go back.
We need to re-look at our work,
try and get our costs down, right?
To whatever the, whatever senior
management has released.
So that's funding limit reconciliation.
Reconciling the amount of
work that needs to be done
with funding limits imposed
or actual funding received.
Okay.